Geordi Readme

Table of Contents

1. Installation
2. Running geordi locally
3. Running a geordi bot
4. Localization
5. Known problems

Appendix A: Example rt tree
Appendix B: Example rt file listing

1. Installation

Geordi is not "./configure && make && make install" software. Setting up geordi is a somewhat awkward manual task, because preparing a chroot tree containing only those files necessary for C++ compilation involves copying into the tree various system and GCC libraries and executables whose location differs wildly from system to system. Since there is no easy way to get a list of precisely those files required for C++ compilation, we'll resort to what is basically a trial and error procedure.

Be warned: If you are relatively new to Linux (and truth be told, even when you're not), installation could very well turn out to be quite a hassle.

Prerequisites

An i386 or x86-64 machine
GNU/Linux ≥ 2.6.10
GCC/G++ ≥ 4
Boost ≥ 1.33 (Only the headers are needed.)
GHC ≥ 6.10.1

On Ubuntu, it is highly recommended to use GHC packages from the Ubuntu repositories. Use of haskell.org's GHC packages may result in strange "g++: Virtual timer expired" errors.

Some distributions package GHC libraries separately. If, when compiling, you get errors like “Could not find module "Control.Monad.State"”, look for separate mtl and network packages.

Parsec < 3 (Yes, that's a "less than".)
utf8-string ≥ 0.2
readline ≥ 1.0.1.0
Diff ≥ 0.1.2
irc ≥ 0.2.3 (Only needed if you want to run an IRC bot.)

These last five are GHC packages. Depending on where you got your GHC from (and on how your distro packaged it, if at all), some of them may already be installed. Use ghc-pkg list to figure out which ones you need. Then, to install those (assuming no distro package was available), use the following procedure (shown here for utf8-string, but it's the same for the others):

tar xf utf8-string-0.2.tar.gz
cd utf8-string-0.2
runhaskell Setup.lhs configure
runhaskell Setup.lhs build
su -c "runhaskell Setup.lhs install"

It may also be possible to install these with cabal, I have no idea.

Optional step for improved error messages

Do grep get_max_length /usr/include/c++/4.3.0/debug/formatter.h (corrected for your system, of course). If you don't get output, it means that your gcc version does not yet have configurable libstdc++ debug mode error formatter line width, which means that you should do the following manually: in that file, find the value 78, and change it into 780.

(See GCC bug 31518 for more information.)

Installation procedure

The following is a list of steps needed to set up the environment geordi runs in. Don't copy&paste this into your terminal, this is not a shell script! It is intended to be read and interpreted by a human.

Assuming you have cd'd into the "geordi" directory obtained through darcs (or extracted from a snapshot), do the following:

chmod +x scripts/*   # darcs is not yet aware of executability
scripts/compile-base   # To produce the ./geordi-local, and ./geordi-testsuite executables.
scripts/compile-irc   # To produce ./geordi-irc. Only needed if you actually want to run a geordi IRC bot.
Edit the compile-config file to your liking. Check that the g++ path refers to the actual g++ binary, not some wrapper that adds output coloring or something.
On Debian and Ubuntu, replace group = "nobody" with group = "nogroup" in jail-config.
scripts/mkrt   # Creates a directory called "rt", which will be our chroot root, and copies various files into it that GCC needs in order to function.
scripts/compile-prelude   # Produces rt/prelude.hpp.gch, rt/prelude.a, and libtpreload.so.0.0.
sudo scripts/trycompile   # This might give errors about missing .o files and libraries. Copy those into rt until rt/t is produced successfully.

The recommended way to copy files into rt is using

cp -L --parents /some/system/file rt/

Here, -L makes cp follow symbolic links, and --parents makes it copy to the same path within rt.

For libstdc++ and libm, use the shared (.so) versions, not the static (.a) versions.

If, while doing this step, you decide (out of sheer desperation) at some point to just copy entire gcc directories into rt (which in itself is not completely unreasonable), make sure that there is no collect2 binary in rt (it confuses geordi).

sudo chroot rt /t   # This may complain a bit more about missing libraries, which again should be copied into rt. Eventually, it should print "9".
find rt -perm -o+w   # This should list exactly four files: rt/t.o, rt/t.s, rt/t.cpp, and rt/t.
find rt -user nobody   # This should find nothing.
find rt -perm -4000   # This should find nothing either.
sudo ./geordi-local "<< 'x'"   # If this does not print 'x', something's wrong.
To get an idea of what rt could look like, look at the example rt tree and the example rt file list.
A modest testsuite can now be run with sudo ./geordi-testsuite (recommended).

2. Running geordi locally

geordi-local lets one test snippets locally (that is, without connecting to any IRC server).

Usage: sudo ./geordi-local [option]... [request]...

Request syntax is described in the manual, except that here the nickname (and colon/comma) must be omitted.

Options:

-h / --help

Display help and exit.

If any requests are specified, they are evaluated and their results are shown. If the first request starts with a request option, interject “--” to prevent it from being interpreted as a command option.

If no requests are specified, the program goes into a Read-Eval-Print-Loop.

3. Running a geordi bot

Regarding the need for root permissions

Starting an IRC bot with root permissions should make one seriously nervous. Geordi requires root permissions only because chroot(2) does. Geordi chroots into rt as one of the first things it does on startup, and changes to the user and group specified in jail-config before it starts responding to IRC messages.

3.1 IRC

Usage: sudo ./geordi-irc [option]...

Options:

-c <file> / --config <file>

Load bot configuration from <file> instead of "irc-config".

-h / --help

Display help and exit.

NickServ identification

To have the bot identify to NickServ, change the following line in irc-config:

  , nick_pass = Nothing

into:

  , nick_pass = Just "mypassword"

Auto-reconnect

Geordi does not auto-reconnect. For that, just use something like while true; do ./geordi-irc; sleep 120; done

Connecting to multiple networks

Make config files for the different networks. Then run one geordi-irc instance for each network, passing -c arguments pointing to the respective config files. The rt directory will be safely shared.

Censoring phrases

Some networks automatically kick or ban clients that utter certain phrases (like botnet commands). To prevent a geordi bot from uttering these, list regexes for them in irc-config. E.g.:

  , censor = ["some naughty phrase", "some wicked utterance"]

4. Localization

To get compiler diagnostics (and some (but not all) other geordi messages) in a locale of your choice, copy the following into rt (preserving paths, for example using cp --parents):

/usr/lib/locale/foo_BAR.utf8/*
/usr/share/locale/foo/LC_MESSAGES/{cpplib,gcc,libc,libstdc++,opcodes}.mo

These paths might differ somewhat on your system.

You may need to install a separate GCC locales package or other kind of language pack for your distro, to get the files above.

Furthermore, not all of the files above may be available for your locale; copy those that are.

Additionally, the LC_ALL environment variable must be set to foo_BAR.utf8 when geordi is started. Since sudo clears environment variables, this means you'll have to use something like:

sudo env LC_ALL=foo_BAR.utf8 ./geordi-...

5. Known problems

Because geordi-irc connects as root, IRC servers that query ident may get a root response and may decide to reject the connection. (Quakenet is known to do this.)

Appendix A: Example rt tree

      rt
      |-- lib64
      |   |-- ld-linux-x86-64.so.2
      |   |-- libc.so.6
      |   |-- libgcc_s.so.1
      |   `-- libm.so.6
      |-- libtpreload.so.0.0
      |-- lock
      |-- prelude.a
      |-- prelude.hpp.gch
      |-- t
      |-- t.cpp
      |-- t.o
      |-- t.s
      |-- terse.hpp
      `-- usr
          |-- bin
          |   |-- as
          |   |-- g++
          |   `-- ld
          `-- lib64
              |-- crt1.o
              |-- crti.o
              |-- crtn.o
              |-- gcc
              |   `-- x86_64-suse-linux
              |       `-- 4.1.2
              |           |-- cc1plus
              |           |-- crtbegin.o
              |           |-- crtend.o
              |           |-- libgcc.a
              |           |-- libgcc_s.so
              |           `-- libstdc++.so
              |-- libbfd-2.17.50.0.5.so
              |-- libc.so
              |-- libc_nonshared.a
              |-- libm.so
              |-- libmcheck.a
              |-- libstdc++.so.6
              `-- libstdc++.so.6.0.8
    

Appendix B: Example rt file listing

      rt:
      total 69M
      drwxr-xr-x 2 eelis users  184 2007-12-25 01:14 lib64
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users  50K 2008-05-15 16:39 libtpreload.so.0.0
      -rw-r--r-- 1 eelis users    0 2007-12-25 01:40 lock
      -rw-r--r-- 1 eelis users 123K 2007-12-25 01:15 prelude.a
      -rw-r--r-- 1 eelis users  68M 2007-12-25 01:15 prelude.hpp.gch
      -rwxrwxrwx 1 eelis users  53K 2007-12-25 01:41 t
      -rw-rw-rw- 1 eelis users   61 2007-12-25 01:41 t.cpp
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 1.3K 2007-12-13 17:06 terse.hpp
      -rw-rw-rw- 1 eelis users  12K 2007-12-25 01:41 t.o
      -rw-rw-rw- 1 eelis users  28K 2007-12-25 01:41 t.s
      drwxr-xr-x 4 eelis users   96 2007-12-25 01:29 usr

      rt/lib64:
      total 2.2M
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 139K 2007-12-13 17:07 ld-linux-x86-64.so.2
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 1.6M 2007-12-13 17:07 libc.so.6
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users  59K 2007-12-13 17:08 libgcc_s.so.1
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 400K 2007-12-25 01:14 libm.so.6

      rt/usr:
      total 0
      drwxr-xr-x 2 eelis users 120 2007-12-13 17:07 bin
      drwxr-xr-x 3 eelis users 368 2007-12-25 01:41 lib64

      rt/usr/bin:
      total 2.3M
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 343K 2007-12-13 17:07 as
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 139K 2007-12-13 17:07 g++
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 1.9M 2007-12-13 17:07 ld

      rt/usr/lib64:
      total 4.0M
      -rw-r--r-- 1 eelis users 3.5K 2007-12-13 17:07 crt1.o
      -rw-r--r-- 1 eelis users 3.2K 2007-12-13 17:07 crti.o
      -rw-r--r-- 1 eelis users 2.7K 2007-12-13 17:07 crtn.o
      drwxr-xr-x 3 eelis users   88 2007-12-13 17:07 gcc
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 1.7M 2007-12-13 17:07 libbfd-2.17.50.0.5.so
      -rw-r--r-- 1 eelis users  21K 2007-12-13 17:10 libc_nonshared.a
      -rw-r--r-- 1 eelis users  253 2007-12-13 17:10 libc.so
      -rw-r--r-- 1 eelis users 1.6K 2007-12-13 17:07 libmcheck.a
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 400K 2007-12-25 01:11 libm.so
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 948K 2007-12-25 01:07 libstdc++.so.6
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 948K 2007-12-25 01:07 libstdc++.so.6.0.8

      rt/usr/lib64/gcc:
      total 0
      drwxr-xr-x 3 eelis users 72 2007-12-13 17:07 x86_64-suse-linux

      rt/usr/lib64/gcc/x86_64-suse-linux:
      total 0
      drwxr-xr-x 2 eelis users 216 2007-12-25 01:31 4.1.2

      rt/usr/lib64/gcc/x86_64-suse-linux/4.1.2:
      total 7.0M
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 5.9M 2007-12-13 17:07 cc1plus
      -rw-r--r-- 1 eelis users 2.4K 2007-12-13 17:07 crtbegin.o
      -rw-r--r-- 1 eelis users 1.9K 2007-12-13 17:07 crtend.o
      -rw-r--r-- 1 eelis users 113K 2007-12-13 17:08 libgcc.a
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users  59K 2007-12-13 17:08 libgcc_s.so
      -rwxr-xr-x 1 eelis users 948K 2007-12-25 01:10 libstdc++.so
    